<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>The blog of Eric Chan</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000"/>
 <updated>2019-05-18T08:09:08-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Eric Chan</name>
   <email>eric.chan.24@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Classifying Animals Using Machine Learning</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/classification/random%20forrest/2019/05/15/Classifying-Animals-Using-Machine-Learning/"/>
   <updated>2019-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/classification/random%20forrest/2019/05/15/Classifying-Animals-Using-Machine-Learning</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;head&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.wrap {
    width: 300px;
    position: relative;
}

.wrap img {
    float: left;
    height: 20px;
}

.wrap h2 {
    line-height: 20px;
    &lt;!-- top: 33px;
    left: 50px; --&gt;
    &lt;!-- display: inline; --&gt;
}
tr.dark {
    background-color: #141866;
    color: #ffffff;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\assets\img\2019-05-May\2019-05-19-Classifying-Animals-Using-Machine-Learning\mini_highland_cow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mini Highland Cow&quot; width=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a mini highland cow. From the image, we see that it has hair, a tail,
and four legs. Some other things that we know about this animal is that it has
teeth and it produces milk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mini highland cow’s attributes are what are called the features of the
animal. The class it belongs to is the mammal class. My goal is to develop a
model that maps from the features of an animal to its class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data
I used a data set from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/datasets/zoo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UCI Machine Learning repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\assets\img\2019-05-May\2019-05-19-Classifying-Animals-Using-Machine-Learning\animal_classes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Animal Classes&quot; width=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The animals are divided into seven classes. A particularly interesting class is
the non-insect invertebrate class. It includes are a variety of animals from
worms, arachnids, crustaceans, mollusks, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\assets\img\2019-05-May\2019-05-19-Classifying-Animals-Using-Machine-Learning\number_of_animals_by_class.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Number of Animals by Class&quot; width=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 101 animals in the data set. There were only five reptiles and four
amphibians. This is important to keep in mind during the splitting of the data.
I want at least one example of reptile and amphibian in my testing data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-exploration-preprocessing-and-cleaning&quot;&gt;Data exploration, preprocessing, and cleaning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a clean data set with no missing values or outliers. The only non-binary feature was the number of legs of each animal. I scaled the number of legs to values between 0 and 1 using a max-min scaler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modeling&quot;&gt;Modeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many algorithms to choose for classification. There is a rule of thumb for logistic regression requiring ten training observations per feature to have properly calibrated model probabilities. I decided to not use logistic regression. Naive Bayes has the assumption that the features used are independent. Since I had features such as “Does this animal have fins” and “Does this animal live in the water”, my features were not independent. I decided not to use naive bayes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built four models and compared the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\assets\img\2019-05-May\2019-05-19-Classifying-Animals-Using-Machine-Learning\four_model_accuracy_barh.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Four Model Accuracy&quot; width=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These models were built without any tuning of hyperparameters. Random forest
and decision tree were producing high accuracy and moved forward with these
algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used randomized grid search to tune the hyperparameters for a decision tree
and random forest model. Random forest produced the best results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\assets\img\2019-05-May\2019-05-19-Classifying-Animals-Using-Machine-Learning\confusion_matrix_random_forest.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Confusion Matrix Random Forest&quot; width=&quot;650px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The random forest model correctly classified every observation in the test set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion
I made a model that maps from animal features to the class of that animal using
random forest. The model was trained on 81 observations and tested on 20
observation. It had 100% accuracy on the test set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made an &lt;a href=&quot;https://animal-classifier.herokuapp.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;interactive app&lt;/a&gt; that shows how the model works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for this project can be found on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ericchan24/Animal-Classification&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
